Guide to the Jack Margolin Photograph Collection 1950-1996 PR 316
New-York Historical Society
Jack Margolin Photograph Collection
1950-1996
New-York Historical Society
PR 316
1.25 Linear feet (3 boxes, 84 photographs)
This collection consists of 84 black and white photographs of New York scenes between 1950-1996. The photographs were taken in Manhattan, Queens and Brooklyn and depict people in cafeterias and automats, subway scenes, biking, kids playing in a hydrant, and various protests.
Provenance
Gift of Sandra Margolin and Roberta Margolin, 2015.
Access Restrictions
Available by advance appointment only. To schedule an appointment, contact the Print Room Librarian at printroom@nyhistory.org. Photocopying undertaken by staff only. Limited to twenty exposures of stable, unbound material per day. (Researchers may not accrue unused copy amounts from previous days.)
Arrangement Note
Photographs are arranged in the numeric order assigned by the photographer.
Scope and Contents Note
This collection consists of 84 black and white (gelatin silver) photographs of New York scenes taken between 1950-1996 by amateur photographer Jack Margolin. The photographs are mounted on board; some have stickers from the Fresh Meadows Camera Club. Images include scenes in Manhattan, Queens and Brooklyn, depicting workers and diners in cafeterias and automats, subway scenes, biking, kids playing in a hydrant, and protests for women's rights and against the Vietnam War. The numbers and titles assigned by Margolin are set forth in the container list below.
Biographical Note
Jack Margolin was born in 1914 in Brooklyn to Russian-Jewish immigrants. He trained as a linotype operator and worked for several newspapers (The New York Times, Daily News, New York Post) before opening his own small printing company in 1961, which specialized in math and science textbooks published by McGraw-Hill. In 1962, Margolin married Pearl Klein. They had three daughters and lived in Bayside, Queens.
Largely self-taught, Margolin began taking photographs in his 20's. After retiring in 1976, Margolin devoted himself to photography full-time. He was a member of several camera clubs (Fresh Meadows, Metropolitan, Queens) and participated in numerous juried shows. He died in New York in 1996.
- 1. "Early Morning" Garment District, 1985 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 1)
- 2. "FDR Drive at Night", undated (Offsite-box 1, Folder 1)
- 3. "Brooklyn Bridge Dusk", undated (Offsite-box 1, Folder 1)
- 4. "Twin Towers; Another View -- Night", undated (Offsite-box 1, Folder 2)
- 5. "Skyscrapers, No. 1, Geometry", undated (Offsite-box 1, Folder 2)
- 6. "Skyscraper No. 2 -- Reflections", undated (Offsite-box 1, Folder 2)
- 7. "Window Washers in the Sky", undated (Offsite-box 1, Folder 3)
- 8. "Early Morning Bayside, Queens, NY", undated (Offsite-box 1, Folder 3)
- 9. "Northern Boulevard Reflections" Queens, NY, undated (Offsite-box 1, Folder 3)
- 10. "Biking Across the 59th St. Bridge", undated (Offsite-box 1, Folder 4)
- 11. "Summer Hydrant Play", 1985 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 4)
- 12. "Seventh Avenue in the Rain", undated (Offsite-box 1, Folder 4)
- 13. "Street Shopping -- Flushing, NY", undated (Offsite-box 1, Folder 5)
- 14. "Asian/English Ads," Flushing, NY, undated (Offsite-box 1, Folder 5)
- 15. "Asian, English Commerce" Flushing, NY, undated (Offsite-box 1, Folder 5)
- 16. "Chinese Food Court" Flushing, NY, undated (Offsite-box 1, Folder 6)
- 17. "Weight Loss Billboard" Flushing, NY, undated (Offsite-box 1, Folder 6)
- 18. "Korean Food Court" Flushing, NY, undated (Offsite-box 1, Folder 6)
- 19. "Well Fed in Cafeteria", undated (Offsite-box 1, Folder 7)
- 20. "Cafeteria Letter-Writing Reflections", undated (Offsite-box 1, Folder 6)
- 21. "Waitress Coffee Shop" 21st Street and 5th Avenue, NYC, undated (Offsite-box 1, Folder 7)
- 22. "BakeOven Cafeteria 4 Men in Hats." 7th Avenue and 31sdt Street, NYC, 1993 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 8)
- 23. "BakeOven Cafeteria -- Man in a Hat," 7th Avenue, 31st Street, NYC, undated (Offsite-box 1, Folder 8)
- 24. "Smoking in the BakeOven Cafe," 7th Avenue and 31st Street, NYC, undated (Offsite-box 1, Folder 8)
- 25. "Huddled Smoker Automat" 7th Avenue and 23rd Street, NYC, undated (Offsite-box 1, Folder 8)
- 26. "Retired Street Worker -- Automat" 7th Avenue and 23rd Street, NYC, undated (Offsite-box 1, Folder 9)
- 27. "Self-Service Paradise Cafe" 6th Avenue and 23rd Street, NYC, undated (Offsite-box 1, Folder 9)
- 28. "Counterman Flat Iron Cafe" 5th Avenue and 21st Street, NYC, 1970 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 1)
- 29. "Julio," Rice and Beans Cafe, 5th Avenue and 21st Street, NYC, 1993 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 1)
- 30. "Stanley, Cafe Counterman", 1995 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 1)
- 31. "Specialties of the Day." Kosher Deli, 1994 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 2)
- 32. "Bartender, Bayside Tavern" Queens NYC, 1990 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 2)
- 33. "Having A Drink, Bayside Tavern." Queens, NYC, 1990 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 2)
- 34. "Waiting for the LIRR," Bayside, NY, undated (Offsite-box 2, Folder 3)
- 35. "Subway Platform -- Winter." Bayside, NY, undated (Offsite-box 2, Folder 3)
- 36. "Subway: 2 Women in Matching Hats", 1995 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 3)
- 37. "On the Flushing Line -- Pensive Man", 1995 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 4)
- 38. "On the Flushing Line -- Conversation", 1995 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 4)
- 39. Subway -- "Where Imagination Runs Wild", 1995 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 4)
- 40. Subway -- "Travel Companions" Ad, 1995 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 5)
- 41. Subway -- "Side by Side", 1994 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 5)
- 42. Subway -- "Serious", 1995 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 5)
- 43. Subway -- "Turbaned", 1995 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 6)
- 44. Subway -- "Reading", 1995 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 6)
- 45. Subway -- "Couple in Black", 1992 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 6)
- 46. Subway -- "Family", 1992 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 7)
- 47. Subway -- "Teenage Girls", 1995 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 7)
- 48. Subway -- "Homestyle, 90's Style" Ad, 1995 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 7)
- 49. Subway -- "Reading the Newspaper", 1995 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 8)
- 50. "Walter B. Cooke Funeral Billboard", undated (Offsite-box 2, Folder 8)
- 51. "Digging in the Trash," The Bowery, 1985 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 8)
- 52. "Daring Night Manhattan Street Scene", undated (Offsite-box 2, Folder 9)
- 53. "Painting Traffic Light" NYC, undated (Offsite-box 2, Folder 9)
- 54. "Fish Monger Under the El" NYC, undated (Offsite-box 2, Folder 9)
- 55. "Carrying Clothes, Garment District", undated (Offsite-box 2, Folder 10)
- 56. "Food Courts," Lexington Avenue and 53rd Street, undated (Offsite-box 2, Folder 10)
- 57. "A Dunkin Donuts View of Times Square", 1992 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 10)
- 58. [Cat in store window] 6th Avenue Donut Shop, 1965 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 1)
- 59. "On the Phone," Times Square Tourist Shop, 1990 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 1)
- 60. "Caps for Sale," Flushing, NY, undated (Offsite-box 3, Folder 1)
- 61. "Orchard Street Market," Lower East Side, NY, 1995 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 2)
- 62. "Atlantic Avenue Flea Market," Brooklyn, NY, undated (Offsite-box 3, Folder 2)
- 63. "Broadway NY Street Vendor", 1992 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 2)
- 64. "Candy Man," 6th Avenue, 1960 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 3)
- 65. "Custom Sandals 22.0" Greenwich Village, 1980 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 3)
- 66. "Women's Strike for Equality with Bella Abzug #1," 5th Avenue NYC, 1970 August 26 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 3)
- 67. "Women's Strike for Equality with Bella Abzug #2" 5th Avenue NYC, 1970 August 26 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 4)
- 68. "Free Abortion on Demand" Women's Demonstration, 5th Avenue, 1970 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 4)
- 69. "Fuck the System" Vietnam War Protest NYC, 1970 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 4)
- 70. "Out Now!" Vietnam War Protest, NYC, 1970 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 5)
- 71. "War Protestor In the Rain," NYC, 1970 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 5)
- 72. "Giving the Peace Sign," Vietnam War Protest, NYC, 1970 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 5)
- 73. "Tough Cop, Labor Day Parade" East 47th Street, NYC, 1993 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 5)
- 74. "Times Square Photo Shoot #1", undated (Offsite-box 3, Folder 6)
- 75. "Times Square Photo Shoot #2", undated (Offsite-box 3, Folder 6)
- 76. "Holy Men" (Hare Krishna), NYC, 1975 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 6)
- 77. "Greenwich Village Hippies", undated (Offsite-box 3, Folder 7)
- 78. "Lovers Plus One," Sculpture on 7th Avenue, NYC, 1992 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 7)
- 79. "Intermission at the Met," Lincoln Center, NYC, 1990 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 7)
- 80. "Four Figures (Shadows & Light)," Canarsie, Brooklyn, NY, undated (Offsite-box 3, Folder 8)
- 81. "On the Bench," Central Park, NY, 1990 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 8)
- 82. "Russian Jews" Brighton Beach, Brooklyn, NY, 1990 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 8)
- 83. "Card Players," Bayside, NY, undated (Offsite-box 3, Folder 9)
- 84. "Waiting for the First Race," Belmont Park, NY, 1985 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 9)
- no number [man in recording studio -- unmounted], undated (Offsite-box 3, Folder 9)